<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse occasioned vpon the late defeat, giuen to the arch-rebels, Tyrone and Odonnell, by the right Honourable the Lord Mountioy, Lord Deputie of Ireland, the 24. of December, 1601. being Christmas Eaue and the yeelding vp of Kinsale shortly after by Don Iohn to his Lordshippe: by Raph Byrchensha Esquire, Controller Generall of the musters in Ireland. Seene and allowed.</title>
            <author>Byrchensha, Raph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104603</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840336</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840336</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4833</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16160)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4833)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1127:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse occasioned vpon the late defeat, giuen to the arch-rebels, Tyrone and Odonnell, by the right Honourable the Lord Mountioy, Lord Deputie of Ireland, the 24. of December, 1601. being Christmas Eaue and the yeelding vp of Kinsale shortly after by Don Iohn to his Lordshippe: by Raph Byrchensha Esquire, Controller Generall of the musters in Ireland. Seene and allowed.</title>
                  <author>Byrchensha, Raph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[34] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Bradock] for M[atthew] L[ownes] and are to be sould in Saint Dunstans Church-yarde.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E¹.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discourse vpon the defeate of the rebels in Ireland.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devonshire, Charles Blount, --  Earl of, 1563-1606 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Tyrone's Rebellion, 1597-1603 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE occaſioned vpon the late defeat, giuen to the Arch-rebels, <hi>Tyrone and Odonnell, by the right</hi> Honourable the Lord <hi>Mountioy,</hi> Lord <hi>Deputie of Ireland, the 24. of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1601. being</hi> Chriſtmas <hi>Eaue:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the yeelding vp of <hi>Kinſale</hi> ſhortly after <hi>by Don Iohn to his Lordſhippe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By RAPH BYRCHENSHA Eſquire, Controller <hi>Generall of the muſters in Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Si Deus nobiſcum, quis contra nos?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON ¶ Printed for <hi>M. L.</hi> and are to be ſould in Saint Dunſtans Church-yarde. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Right Honourable L. <hi>Charles Blunt, Baron of Mountioy, Captaine</hi> of the Caſtles and Forts of Porchmouth, <hi>L. Deputie of Ireland, and knight of the moſt Honourable order of the Garter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y your Lordſhips and the reſt of the Councels Letters at <hi>Kinſale,</hi> bearing date the 27. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> laſt, 1601. directed to the right H. the Lord Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour, and the reſt of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie Councel here your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe aduertiſed your happy and bleſſed ſucceſſe (by Gods moſt gracious prouidence) obtained ouer the Arch-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels <hi>Tyrone, Oddonell,</hi> and the reſt of the rebels and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh inuadours, vpon Chriſtmas Eaue, being the 24. of <hi>December:</hi> which moſt famous victorie and great hand of the Almightie, I had aduertiſement the ſixt of this preſent, that 14. Prieſts of the rebels were diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, to perſwade and incenſe the vulgar and common ſort, that the rebels &amp; Spanyards receiued no ſuch loſſe or damage as your Lordſhips ſaid Letter deliuered: nor as the common brute moſt confidently conceiued and knew to be: by which practiſe they meant the more ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to holde in and continue their faction. Whereupon I thought it both reaſonable, and diſcourſe agreeing to the nature of trueth, to make knowne to the world, that
<pb facs="tcp:4833:3"/> the rebels loſſe &amp; damage was not leſſe then your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſaid Letter mentioned, but in higher meaſure and greater preiudice to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then that Letter expreſſed: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the world may ſee the falſhood and deceipt of theſe beaſtly Prieſts, &amp; the drift of theſe rebels and traitours to drawe vnconſtant men and wauering ſubiectes to their curſed purpoſes: I confeſſe I haue very coldly &amp; barely handled this ſubiect, and rather dimmed and diminiſhed the worth &amp; dignitie thereof, then beautified and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame with matter or method: wherein I humbly beſeech your Lordſhippes pardon, as alſo in my boldnes in preſuming vpon ſo nice an argument. But pearles and precious ſtones require no ornaments to ſet them forth: neither doth the originall cauſe of my writing, neede or aſke any floriſh my ſelfe or any other mortall man can make in the ſame, being a worke directed and purpoſed by the power &amp; ſtrength of Iehoua, the great God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth: and effected &amp; performed by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips valour and worthineſſe, being Gods inſtrument appointed for the accompliſhment thereof: which are matters more then ſufficient in themſelues to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the cauſe to the world. And ſo in all humble manner I wil leaue my poore labour to your Lordſhips Honourable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and fauourable cenſure, and your Lordſhips perſon to be protected vnder the bleſſed wings of the Almighty. From my houſe in <hi>Dublin</hi> the 30. of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> 1601.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble in all duty and ſeruice, Raph Birchenſha</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:3"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader, whether counterfeit or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Papiſts: open or publike Recuſants: or what kinde of Papiſts ſoeuer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe the Subiect, whereupon I chiefly haue fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this diſcourſe, aimeth only to lay open the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hand of God lately ſhewed to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, and performed by her loyall and faithfull Subiect the <hi>L. MOVNTIOYE, L.</hi> Deputy of this Land, against the inſolent, traiterous, and rebellious vſurpation of <hi>Tyrone, Odonnell,</hi> and all other open and diſcouered rebels: And that among other his coloured and ſhadowed courſes for his rebellion, this principally was one: namely, to reforme religion, and for his and their conſcience ſake. Whoſe religion (if he haue any at all, as I aſſure my ſelfe he hath none) is but meere Athiſme, and himſelfe a damned ſlaue in hell, without harty repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and ſpeedy conuerſion. And for that the religion whereof he makes outward ſhew &amp; profeſſion, is according to the Romiſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Church, taught, deliuered, and brought hither into this Realme of Ireland from the ſhambles &amp; ſlaughter-houſe of ſoules, I meane the Church of Rome: and maintained, defended, and earneſtly vrged by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ the Pope of Rome, that man of ſinne: and by his fugitiues, runnagates, and traiterous male-contented ſubiects of all Princes in Chriſtendom flocking ſtill thither: I meane his Seminaries, Ieſuits, Prieſts, and Fryers: Who cloſely creepe and ſteale into this Land in diſguiſed and counterfeited manner: and by whom infinite ſoules of men haue beene and are ſeduced and drawne away from the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and obedience of his will, to follow tradition, ſuperſtition, and mans inuention, to the great danger of their ſoules, without ſpeedy amendment. In regard whereof, it may pleaſe you with patience and in brotherly loue and affection: which euery faithfull and true Chriſtian ought to haue, the one with the other, but with a ſingle eye and well diſpoſed hart, conſider of theſe ſpeciall points inſuing: by
<pb facs="tcp:4833:4"/> which the Church of Rome is made ſo glorious, and which heads are alſo ſo ſtifly and ſtoutly maintained and taught by that ſide: and then to iudge and cenſure whither the Church of Rome be the true ſpouſe of Christ or no: or whether on the contrarie, it be not the falſe Church, and the apparant ſinke and ſynagogue of Sathan.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> First then, whereas the Church of Rome will haue their Church to be knowne to be the true Church, by the viſibilitie, antiquity, and multitude thereof, and ſo to be ſeene with the outward eye, and poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at with the finger: yet you ſhall finde that viſibilitie, antiquitie, and multitude are not the markes of the true Church: but a little flocke few in number, and yet of greateſt antiquitie: as by theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces foorth of Gods word may appeare. For I pray tell me where the Church was viſible, when being aſſembled at Ieruſalem, there aroſe<note place="margin">Act. 8. 1.</note> a great perſecution against it, inſomuch as they were all diſpearſed and ſcattered? And let them tell me, where, or how the Church was viſible when Christ was ſmitten, and all the rest was ſcattered and<note place="margin">Matth. 12. 17.</note> hid, and concealed themſelues. Doth not S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Reuelation<note place="margin">Reuel. 12. 6. 7.</note> teſtifie expreſly, That the Church of Christ, ſignified there by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, fled into a deſert or wilderneſſe, where ſhe had a place prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for her of God, and where ſhe could not for a certaine ſeaſon be found of the perſecutors? Where was the Church in the time of <hi>Elias</hi> the Prophet? When he ſaid, <hi>They haue forſaken thy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings. 19. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>they haue deſtroyed thine Altar, and ſlaine thy Prophets with the ſword, and I am left alone.</hi> Againe, it is written in the 2. of<note place="margin">2. Kings. 16.</note> Kings the 16. that <hi>vnder the raigne of Achas, there was taken a patterne of the Altar of the Idolaters of Damaſcus, and Vrias the High Prieſt remooued the Altar of the Lord.</hi> Whereby it appeareth that the Prieſthood was corrupted, the Altar remooued, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the ſacrifice ceaſed. Now I truſt there is no Papist ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent to ſay, that either the true Church was in the Scribes and Phariſies, or in the time of <hi>Achas, Manaſſes,</hi> and many other Kings of Iſraell, ſo viſible and populous as they would haue it: but that the Church of Chriſt were in that ſmall number, whereſoeuer diſperſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Church of Rome holdes that ignorance is the mother
<pb facs="tcp:4833:4"/> of deuotion: but Christ ſaith ignorance is the mother of error: ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>You erre not knowing the Scriptures:</hi> and Chriſt biddeth the<note place="margin">Matth. 22. 29. Ioh. 5. 39. Coloſſ. 3. 16. Acts. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> people to ſearch the Scripture. <hi>Paul</hi> commaunded that the word of God ſhould dwell plentiouſly in the people, whereby they might teach themſelues: and the <hi>Berenas</hi> examined the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the Church of Rome teacheth, that the Scriptures ought to be taught in a ſtrange tongue. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: <hi>He that</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeaketh in a ſtrange tongue; ſpeaketh not vnto men, but vnto God, for no man heareth him, howbeit in the ſpirit he ſpeaketh ſecret things. He that ſpeaketh in a ſtrange language edifieth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. I would that you all ſpake ſtrange languages, but rather that you prophecied. For greater is he that prophecieth, then he that ſpeaketh diuers tongues, except he expound it, that the Church may receiue edification. And now brethren, if I come vnto you ſpeaking diuers tongues, what ſhall it profit you, &amp;c.</hi> Moreouer, things without life which giue a ſound, whether it be a Harpe or a Pipe, except they make a diſtinction in the ſound, how ſhall it be knowne what is piped or harped? So likewiſe yee by the tongue, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you vtter words which haue ſignification, how ſhall it be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what is ſpoken, for you ſhall ſpeake in the ayre.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, the Church of Rome doth teach there is a Purgatorie. Christ in the Goſpell ſheweth onely two places, namely heauen and hell: Chriſt ſaid to the theefe, <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16. Luke. 23. 43.</note> 
               <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, he that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth my words and beleeueth him that ſent me, hath eternall life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 25. Phil. 1. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and commeth not into condemnation, but paſſeth from death to life.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I couet to be diſſolued and to be with Chriſt.</hi> Againe, <hi>For we know, that when this earthly tabernacle of ours is diſſolued, we haue a building of God not made with hands, but</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 1. Reuel. 14. 13.</note> 
               <hi>eternall in the heauens.</hi> Againe, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from hencefoorth they reſt from their labours, and their workes follow them.</hi> And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> telleth the Saints and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 9.</note> of God, and aſſureth them of it, <hi>That the end of their faith is the ſaluation of their ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, the Church of Rome teacheth, that ſince the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> man hath free-will: Whereas God ſaith, <hi>After that time that the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> 
               <hi>imaginations of mens harts are onely euill euery day.</hi> Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Iere. 7.</note> 
               <hi>No man can come vnto me, except the father draw him.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Rom. 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Conuert thou me and I ſhall be conuerted.</hi> Alſo, <hi>There is not one<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> that doth good, no not one.</hi> Againe, <hi>Without faith it is vnpoſſible<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 23.</note> to pleaſe God:</hi> And againe, <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 15. 1, 2.</note> Alſo, <hi>Except men be ingrafted into him, they can bring foorth no fruits:</hi> beſides many places to like effect.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, the Church of Rome deliuereth the Sacrament but in one kinde, namely bread: Christ ſaith, <hi>Drinke yee all of this cup. Paul</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 27. 1. Cor. 11. 23. 28.</note> 1. Corinthians 11. 23. 28. ſaith, <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seuenthly, the Church of Rome holdeth tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament, and this they would ſeeme to ground vpon theſe words: <hi>This is my body,</hi> which they will haue to be expounded lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally: but why then doe they not expound the other words of Christ literally alſo concerning the cup? For the text ſaith in the 27. and 28. verſes, that <hi>He tooke the cup and ſaid, This is my bloud:</hi> I am ſure they will not ſay that the cup was the bloud of Chriſt, (as the words be,) but they will graunt a figure in thoſe words: namely, that by the cup is meant the wine in it: if then they will admit a figure in this, why may there not be a figure in the other: namely, <hi>This is my body,</hi> ſhould be vnderſtood thus: This bread is a figure of my body, (which was broken for you.) Circumciſion was called the Lords coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, when indeed it was not the couenant: So likewiſe the Paſchall Lambe is called the Paſſeouer, when indeed it was but a ſigne of the Paſſeouer. Christ ſaith, <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith plainely and expreſly, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26. 28. that the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants doe eate bread: and therefore it remaineth bread after the words of conſecration. For if it were tranſubſtantiated into the body of Christ, then were there no bread to eate, but the body of Christ is the thing that ſhould be eaten: but none doth eate the very body of Christ. For if euery communicant did eate the very body of Christ
<pb facs="tcp:4833:5"/> naturally, carnally, and really (as they groſly ſuppoſe,) Christ ſhould haue a number of bodies, which is palpably abſurd and monſtrous to thinke. Beſides, if Christ gaue his body to be eaten really by his Diſciples, at the time of the inſtitution of this Sacrament, what was it that did hang vpon the croſſe on the morrow. Moreouer, S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 21, that as touching the body of Christ, <hi>The heauens muſt containe him to the end of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eightly, the Church of Rome holdeth the Pope hath authority to depoſe Kings and Princes. <hi>God depoſeth the mightie from their ſeates, and exalteth them of low degree.</hi> It is God that teſtifieth of<note place="margin">Luke. 1. Dan. 2. 20. &amp; 4. 14. &amp; 21. 2. Cor. 10. 4. Rom. 13. 1. 2. 3. 4. 1. Pet. 2. 13. Tit. 3. 1.</note> himſelfe; <hi>By me Kings raigne, and Princes haue dominion. Paul</hi> confeſſeth plainely, that the weapons of their warfare are not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, but mightie through God, that is ſpirituall. And it is manifest by the practiſe of the Apoſtles and all their precepts, (commaunding all Chriſtians to obey their rulers, their Kings &amp; Princes, yea though they were perſecutors:) &amp; the Apoſtles neuer had any ſuch authority commited to them. Christ himſelfe ſaith, his kingdome was not of<note place="margin">Ioh. 18. 36. Ioh. 6. 15. Math. 22. 21.</note> this world: and Chriſt himſelfe refuſed to be made a King: Christ himſelfe alſo paid tribute vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and commaunded others to giue the ſame, and all other dueties of ſubiection and obedience to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And Christ hath expreſly forbidden his Apoſtles, &amp; in them all the Miniſters of his Goſpell, all ſuch dominion &amp; ciuill iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaying thus vnto them: <hi>The Kings of the nations raigne ouer</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20. 25. 26 Mar. 10. 42. 43.</note> 
               <hi>them, and they that be great among them beare rule or dominion, but it ſhall not be ſo with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly, the Pope of Rome holds that he hath power to forgiue ſinners. But the Scribes, in the Goſpell could ſay, none can forgiue<note place="margin">Mar. 2. 7. Iob. 14. 4. Eſay. 45. 11.</note> ſinnes but God. <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>Who can bring a cleane thing out of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, there is not one.</hi> And <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking, in the perſon of God: <hi>I euen I am he that putteth away thine iniquities for mine owne ſake, and will not remember thy ſinnes.</hi> And <hi>Paul confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmeth, when he ſaith, Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 33. 34.</note> 
               <hi>of Gods choſen: it is God that iuſtifieth, who ſhall condemne: it is Chriſt which is dead, yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or rather which is riſen againe, who is
<pb facs="tcp:4833:6"/> alſo at the right hand of God, and maketh requeſt alſo for vs.</hi> Againe, <hi>The Lord is ſlow to anger, and of great mercy, and forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 14. 18. Exod. 34. 7.</note> 
               <hi>iniquitie:</hi> And in <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. God ſpeaking in his owne perſon, ſaid: that he reſerueth mercie for thouſands, forgiuing iniquity and tranſgreſſion and ſinne: beſides infinite places to like purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, the Church of Rome doth teach that the Scriptures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine not all things neceſſary to ſaluation: but their vnwritten tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions<note place="margin">10</note> must (as they ſay) be all receiued with equall and like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, for ſo hath the Councell of Trent determined. But S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Theſe things are written that yee may beleeue, and that in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing yee may haue life eternall:</hi> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>The Scriptures are profitable to reprooue, to teach and correct, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>and perfect the man of God:</hi> and further, that <hi>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are able to make men wiſe vnto ſaluation:</hi> and God himſelfe doth ſay, <hi>Yee ſhall put nothing to the word which I command you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> 
               <hi>neither take ought there-from:</hi> Againe, <hi>Whatſoeuer I command</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 12.</note> 
               <hi>you, that take heed you doe, put nothing thereto, nor take ought there-from.</hi> And S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Reuelation ſaith, that <hi>If any man ſhal</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note> 
               <hi>adde to this thing, God ſhall adde vnto him the plagues which are written in this booke, and ſhall take away his part out of the booke of life.</hi> I might yet adde further touching the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Christ. for that the Church of Rome will yeeld that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Christ conſiſteth in theſe three points: namely that he is both a Prophet, a Priest, and a King: which in words they will acknowledge, but in deeds and veritie they doe not. For how miſerably and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly the Church of Rome hath mangled and defaced the reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will of this ſacred Prophet, their vnwritten traditions, popiſh canons, and their owne deuiſes makes too apparant. Touching his Priesthood, which conſisteth in two things, namely, the offering vp of himſelfe once, for a full, perfect, and ſufficient ſacrifice: and his interceſſion to his Father, which remayneth to the worlds end, is ſo pitifully defrauded, abuſed, and diſhonoured by them, as no pen with any modestie can ſet downe: as by their Purgatorie pickepurſe, their propitiatorie maſſes for the quicke and the dead, the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous titles attributed to the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> namely, they call her
<pb facs="tcp:4833:6"/> the Queene of heauen, the gate of Paradiſe, their life &amp; ſweetnes, the treaſure of grace, the refuge of ſinners, &amp; the mediatrix of men: and not onely to her, but to ſaints departed they intreat with like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, and holde them their mediators. Touching how they deale with Chriſt in his rule and gouernement, the Pope he will raigne in mens conſciences, &amp; he will be tituled with <hi>Holy, vniuerſal mother Church which cannot erre, Holy father the Pope: Biſhop vniuerſall: Prince of Prieſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Supreame head of the Church: Vicar of Chriſt: &amp; The admiration of the world, &amp;c.</hi> Touching his iuriſdiction, he chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to himſelfe both the ſwords: that is, both the keyes of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie: and the Scepter of the laitie, not onely ſubduing all Biſhops vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, aduancing himſefe aboue kings and Emperours, cauſing ſome of them to lie vnder his feet, ſome to hold the ſtirrop: kings to lead his horſe by the bridle: ſome to kiſſe his feet: placing and displa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all degrees of people: pretending power and authoritie to inueſt Biſhops, to giue benefices, to spoyle Churches, to giue authoritie to binde &amp; loſe: to call generall Councels: to ſet vp religions, to canonize Saints, to take appeals, to binde conſciences, to make lawes, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with the law &amp; word of God, to deliuer from purgatory, and to command Angels, &amp;c. Whereby appeares, as he preſumeth to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Chriſt in this world, ſo would he if he knew how alſo expulſe him from heauen. And now gentle Reader, in equall ballance, ſingle eye, and honeſt heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cenſure whether the Church of Rome be the ſpouſe of Chriſt or no: &amp; whether the word of God allow &amp; warrant his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. I cannot ſtand longer to inlarge of his doctrine (which is moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious to Chriſt &amp; his Church: nor lay downe his life, which is moſt deteſtable to all men that hath any ſparke of the true knowledge of Gods word:) but abruptly haſten to an end, becauſe you may perceiue I haue but in briefe paſt ouer the particulars: for to diſcourſe of theſe points would aſke large volumes, not doubting but all indifferent men, may hereby behold vpon what rocke theſe Arch-rebels build their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: if it be true as they ſay, that it is vndertaken in regard of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; their conſcience: alſo that all men, of what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition ſoeuer, who hath ben &amp; is lead still on to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce after the pipe of prieſts, Ieſuits,
<pb facs="tcp:4833:7"/> and Seminaries, who outwardly carry a ſhew of godlineſſe, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly are rauening and deuouring Wolues, may ſee what ground and warrant they find in Gods word, to approoue and allow their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and liues, indefending, maintaining, and ſetting foorth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their master Antichrist the Pope, the diuels ſworne cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion: whoſe creeping in corners, whoſe oyled mouthes, whoſe outward holines, whoſe monſtrous hypocriſie, whoſe maſſes, whoſe dirges, whoſe beades, whoſe crucifixes, whoſe prayers, whoſe vowes, whoſe whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, whoſe croſſes, <hi>Agnus deis,</hi> and perſwaſions, hath but hitherto brought foorth rebellion, diſobedience to Prince, breach of Lawes and gouernment, burning, waſting, ſpoyling, robbing, and in generall almost an vtter ruine and waste of Ireland. Therefore in the feare of God, now come from them, and while it is yet day walke as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the Children of light, turne from theſe ſeducers, their curſed doctrine and ſuperſtitious ceremonies, and imbrace the pure milke of Gods most bleſſed word, and willingly, readily, and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully come to heare the ſame preached and taught, which will be the perfect path for to lead you, the ſtrong ſterne to guide you, the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to light you, and the meane by the mercy of God to ſaue your ſoules. For which euery faithfull Christian doth dayly pray.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, if you be the Lords. Ralph Birchenſha.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:7"/>
            <head>A ¶ DISCOVRSE OCCASIONED <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PON THE LATE DEFEAT GIVEN</hi> to the Arch-rebels TYRONE and ODONNEL, by the <hi>right Honourable the Lord</hi> MOVNTIOY, <hi>L. Deputy</hi> of Ireland. And the yeelding of the Spaniards to <hi>his Lordſhip.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Onder to men, worlds glorie, mightie Lord,</l>
               <l>Earths monarch, Prince of thrones &amp; powers all,</l>
               <l>Peerleſſe for praiſe, famous in factes and deedes,</l>
               <l>Guider of Angels, aide of mortall men:</l>
               <l>Whoſe little finger ſwayes both ſea and lande,</l>
               <l>And turnes the globe of heauen with his hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To gloomie earth all darke and voide of forme,</l>
               <l>His bleſſed breath did giue a happie ſhape:</l>
               <l>His onely word made Sunne, the Moone and Starres,</l>
               <l>And at his will, beaſts, fiſh, and foule tooke life:</l>
               <l>Nothing there was, or is, or that ſhall bee,</l>
               <l>But his ſtrong hand doth guide and rule wee ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Lucifer</hi> great Prince of hell had falne,</l>
               <l>And mad in malice, wrought mans ouerthrow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iehouas</hi> hand the inſtrument did frame,</l>
               <l>To vanquiſh Sathan through the womans ſeed:</l>
               <l>Sweet Chriſt: Chriſt Ieſus was the onely meane,</l>
               <l>That bruiſ'd his head, his heele, and kingdome cleane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:8"/>
               <l>Great was the iudgement this immortall God,</l>
               <l>Vnto the firſt age for their ſinnes did ſhewe:</l>
               <l>Moſt fearefull floods from heauen windowes fell,</l>
               <l>That fifteene cubits mounted bouethe earth:</l>
               <l>All drowned were, from death not one could part,</l>
               <l>But eight, which were incloſed in the Arke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen <hi>Amrophell, Aroch,</hi> and <hi>Tydall</hi> kings,</l>
               <l>VVith <hi>Chedor, Laomer</hi> king of Elam too,</l>
               <l>Made bloodie warre gainſt <hi>Bera</hi> Sodom king,</l>
               <l>And other Peeres that rulde Gomorah then:</l>
               <l>In that ſame valley which men Siddim call,</l>
               <l>King <hi>Bera</hi> and his Peeres were vanquiſht all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe fierce inuaders hauing conqueſt got,</l>
               <l>In triumph beares the ſpoile and prey away:</l>
               <l>But loe, beholde, the Lord did raiſe vp ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Abraham,</hi> who with three hundred men,</l>
               <l>Fought with theſe kings, and made them fly amaine,</l>
               <l>And ſo brought backe their wiues and goods againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen curſed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would not giue conſent,</l>
               <l>The Iſraelites from <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhould depart,</l>
               <l>Though God by <hi>Moyſes</hi> mightie wonders wrought,</l>
               <l>To cauſe him yeeld and giue them leaue to paſſe:</l>
               <l>Yet ſtubbornly proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would aſſay,</l>
               <l>To croſſe Gods will and bring them to decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But loe beholde, when Iſraels hope was gone,</l>
               <l>And ſawe no meane to ſcape or life to ſaue,</l>
               <l>And bloudie <hi>Pharaoh</hi> bent to take reuenge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Then would the Lord make knowne he was a God:</l>
               <l>At his commaund the ſea was made dry land,</l>
               <l>To ſaue his people from inuaders hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:8"/>
               <l>But bloudie <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would not yet relent,</l>
               <l>Although he ſaw a miracle ſo ſtrange,</l>
               <l>But boldly ventred with his horſe and foote,</l>
               <l>Suppoſing that that way was made for him:</l>
               <l>But when in midſt thereof his forces came,</l>
               <l>The ſeas made way, and fiercely on them ranne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and bolde <hi>Abiram,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rigdvp the furrowes of rebelling harts,</l>
               <l>And had two hundred fiftie captaines ſtout,</l>
               <l>To ioyne with them gainſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> Gods chiefe friend:</l>
               <l>Loe what inſued, God hating rebels all,</l>
               <l>The ground doth open, they therein doe fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Arad, Syhon, Og,</hi> three mightie Kings,</l>
               <l>Oppoſde themſelues gainſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> in like caſe:</l>
               <l>And ramd their gates, and ſhut vp all the waies,</l>
               <l>And with fierce fight the Iſraelites did charge:</l>
               <l>Yet God who alwaies for his people ſtands,</l>
               <l>In battaile gaue theſe Kings to <hi>Moyſes</hi> hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Eui, Reken, Zur, Hur,</hi> and <hi>Reba,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fiue potent Kings of Medianits they were,</l>
               <l>Attempting boldly <hi>Phinehas</hi> to charge,</l>
               <l>And rankt their forces gainſt the Lords elect:</l>
               <l>But God that neuer failes to aide the right,</l>
               <l>Gaue theſe fiue Kings to him in the ſame fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Moyſes</hi> had nigh ſpace of fortie yeares,</l>
               <l>Through wilderneſſe, hils, dales, and mountaines wide,</l>
               <l>Gods people guided towards Canaan land,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moyſes</hi> departed, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> tooke the charge:</l>
               <l>And firſt of all his valour for to ſhow,</l>
               <l>He gaue attempt to ſtately Ierycho.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:9"/>
               <l>But what the Lord appoints muſt needes be done.</l>
               <l>For whome God fights, they ſure are to preuaile.</l>
               <l>Mans arme and ſtrength is but too weake a ſtay,</l>
               <l>Small is the meanes by which God winnes the field:</l>
               <l>The voice of trumpets ſhouting therewithall,</l>
               <l>Made ſtony walles, and yron gates to fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When great <hi>Goliah</hi> preſt to plague Gods Church,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe height a cubit fully did containe,</l>
               <l>Of braſſe his helmet cunningly was made,</l>
               <l>His brigandine fiue thouſand ſhickels weigh'd:</l>
               <l>His ſpeare and ſhield were all of pure braſſe,</l>
               <l>His ſpeare in bignes VVeauers beames did paſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then high Iehouah little <hi>Dauid</hi> brought,</l>
               <l>All naked in compare of his ſtrong foe,</l>
               <l>Who in the ſight of all the ſtanders by,</l>
               <l>Into his forehead ſent ſo ſound a ſtroke,</l>
               <l>As downe the monſter fell vpon the earth,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Dauid</hi> there depriu'd him of his breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Far more then theſe Gods regiſter doth yeeld,</l>
               <l>That ſhews his loue and aid to mortall men,</l>
               <l>That hath regard vnto his lawes and heaſt,</l>
               <l>And for his right will wraſtle with the proud:</l>
               <l>For God regards ne horſe, nor ſpeare, nor ſhield,</l>
               <l>For without meanes he makes the ſtout to yeeld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt wicked then are Iriſh rebels breed,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe lawleſſe liues weaues on their web of woe,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe wicked facts <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> paſſe,</l>
               <l>Farre worſe then heathen Pagans of the earth,</l>
               <l>The onely monſters that the world containes,</l>
               <l>And curſed crue whome all good men refraines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:9"/>
               <l>Rebels to God, deſpiſers of his lawes,</l>
               <l>Traitors to Chriſt, depriuers of his right,</l>
               <l>Refuſing ſtill the gifts of holie Ghoſt:</l>
               <l>Breakers of peace, reiecters of the truth,</l>
               <l>Contemners of Gods word and holy writ,</l>
               <l>That guides mens liues the perfect path to hit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Rebels to Prince, rebels to natiue home,</l>
               <l>Traitors to Prince, traitors to countries due,</l>
               <l>Supplanters of all rule and gouernment,</l>
               <l>Infringing lawes, the waſte of Common-weale:</l>
               <l>The brood of wolues, the elder ſonnes of <hi>Cain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The impes of hell, and very markes of ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Champions of hell, borne with bloodie hand,</l>
               <l>Haters of truth, ſworne ſlaues to rape and ſpoyle,</l>
               <l>Authors of miſchiefe: all on murther ſet,</l>
               <l>Masking with faces like ſtrong plates of braſſe:</l>
               <l>Furies of hell, ſhaking their dog-eard locks,</l>
               <l>Like damned ſlaues ſprung from moſt curſed ſtocks.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Breakers of wedlocke, wantons in their liues,</l>
               <l>Moſt bred vp baſtards from their very birth:</l>
               <l>Louers of theft, liuing by theeuing trade,</l>
               <l>Idle in life, like beaſts fed in the ſtall:</l>
               <l>Falſe lying mates, deceitfull and vniuſt,</l>
               <l>Whom God nor man, nor diuell cannot truſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Idolators, ſuperſtitious men,</l>
               <l>Falſe worſhippers, ſworne ſlaues vnto the Pope,</l>
               <l>Truſting to dreames and fained prophecies,</l>
               <l>Obſeruers of old writs that haue no ground:</l>
               <l>More ignorant then beaſts are in their kinde,</l>
               <l>Willing to loſe what chiefe they ought to finde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:10"/>
               <l>Open mainitainers of all runnagates,</l>
               <l>As peeuiſh prieſts and filthie begging Friers,</l>
               <l>Sold Seminaries to the Romiſh Church,</l>
               <l>Falſe traitors to their ſoueraigne Prince and Queene:</l>
               <l>Vilde lothſome locuſts crawld from yond the ſeas,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtinking breaths ingenders ſore diſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That this is true, view Irelands preſent ſtate,</l>
               <l>Which whilome ſate in faire and rich attire,</l>
               <l>Which whilome flow'd in plentie of the earth,</l>
               <l>But now growne naked, feeble, weake and bare:</l>
               <l>Who lately held ſweete peace both neere and farre,</l>
               <l>But now in euery place at deadly iarre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>View now their houſes waſted as they lie,</l>
               <l>View now their fields all barren round about,</l>
               <l>View now their medowes ouergrowne with weedes,</l>
               <l>View their high waies vntroden as they are:</l>
               <l>All honeſt trades are ceaſed very nie,</l>
               <l>And plague on plague you perfectly may ſpie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The old men wander like as men forlorne,</l>
               <l>And women faint for want of ſome reliefe;</l>
               <l>Yong children ſtarue and pine for bread we ſee,</l>
               <l>Moſt of the poore reſemble death in ſhew:</l>
               <l>In ſtinking holes and vilde vnſeemly place,</l>
               <l>Are Cels for ſuch in this their dolefull caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>View well their bogs furd all with bloodie hew,</l>
               <l>View well their faſtnes of the ſelfe ſame ſtampe,</l>
               <l>View well their hedges ſprinkled all with red,</l>
               <l>View well their brookes how bloodie they doe looke:</l>
               <l>The blood that Ireland ſheds from day to day,</l>
               <l>For vengeance cries to God without delay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:10"/>
               <l>What is the cauſe this land in ſuch termes ſtands?</l>
               <l>But only that the people fell from God,</l>
               <l>And brake Gods Sabboths with a mightie hand,</l>
               <l>Forſooke the Preachers of his bleſſed word:</l>
               <l>Apoſtates the moſt of them haue plaid,</l>
               <l>And will not turne for ought that may be ſaid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seminarie prieſts and lying Friers,</l>
               <l>Firſt ſware them, that Gods word they ſhall not heare,</l>
               <l>And teach them their oth vnto their Prince</l>
               <l>May lawfully be broken when they will:</l>
               <l>And ſweares them, that deuoutly they ſhall keepe,</l>
               <l>What ſo the Pope of Rome and themſelues like.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe are the grounds from whence all miſchiefe ſpring,</l>
               <l>Theſe are the cauſes that rebellion is:</l>
               <l>Theſe are the reaſons Spaniards inuade,</l>
               <l>This is the matter no amendment comes:</l>
               <l>For why, the diuell now is buſie ſtill,</l>
               <l>To draw all men to chuſe what beſt he will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O famous Queene, who holds this land by right,</l>
               <l>Whoſe care hath been and is, to cure their ſore:</l>
               <l>What louing fauours hath her Grace beſtowd,</l>
               <l>On mightie men, and ſubiects of this land?</l>
               <l>Whoſe wiſe foreſights in time might ſtop full well,</l>
               <l>The ſtreames from whence theſe miſchiefes ſo do ſwel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But well her Highneſſe hath from time to time,</l>
               <l>Obſerued ſtill this nations wandring thoughts,</l>
               <l>And ſeene into their natures and their liues,</l>
               <l>Who like yong colts and heifers loue to fling,</l>
               <l>That without bits, and bridles, and ſtrong hand,</l>
               <l>Will not be held in peace or reſt to ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:11"/>
               <l>The better therefore to inſtruct their liues,</l>
               <l>As louing fathers vſe vnto their ſonnes,</l>
               <l>To keepe them in a liking of good lawes,</l>
               <l>And to prouide them tutors of good life:</l>
               <l>So did her Grace from time to time elect,</l>
               <l>Graue and wiſe men this land for to direct.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Suſſex</hi> was one worthie of ſuch a charge,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sidney</hi> another held of good account,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fitz Williams</hi> had the like authoritie,</l>
               <l>Lord <hi>Gray</hi> did alſo rule by like commaund:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parret</hi> was choſen to the ſelfeſame place,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ruſſell</hi> held the ſword another ſpace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lord <hi>Burrowes</hi> had the ſoueraigne ſeate alſo,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſſex</hi> was placed in the chaire of ſtate:</l>
               <l>Beſides all theſe Lord Iuſtices bare ſway,</l>
               <l>And vnto them graue Counſellors were ioynd:</l>
               <l>By whoſe aduice and gouernment was thought,</l>
               <l>Vnto good life that Ireland would be brought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beſides the charge for theſe ſame choſen men,</l>
               <l>What ſummes of gold and ſiluer hath been ſpent?</l>
               <l>What maſte of victuals forth of England come?</l>
               <l>What ſtore of powder and munition?</l>
               <l>What Engliſh blood in Ireland hath been ſhed,</l>
               <l>Since firſt theſe Rebels grew vnto a head?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beſides all this, what Iriſh euer was,</l>
               <l>Vpon complaint vnto his ſoueraigne Queene,</l>
               <l>Of wrongs, of loſſe, of iniurie ſuſtaind,</l>
               <l>But in good meaſure he hath iuſtice found?</l>
               <l>Iuſtice and mercie, bountie, loue and all,</l>
               <l>Her princely breaſt hath in this land let fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:11"/>
               <l>Then come all Iriſh borne of honeſt birth,</l>
               <l>In equall ballance lay thy preſent cauſe:</l>
               <l>Did euer ſubiects dealt withall as theſe,</l>
               <l>In ſuch vngratefull ſort reward their Prince?</l>
               <l>No, no, its hard like preſident to finde,</l>
               <l>Subiects to Prince were neuer ſo vnkinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In lieu of all that hath been ſaid before,</l>
               <l>Which were ſufficient motiues to preuaile,</l>
               <l>In any heart where feare of God did reſt:</l>
               <l>What hope is yet in this rebellious man?</l>
               <l>No hope at all, for why his peacocks plume</l>
               <l>Is ſpread abroad the land for to conſume.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This rauening kite, this carren crow by kinde,</l>
               <l>Theſe ſeauen long winters with his bloodie hands</l>
               <l>Haue waſted, ſpoild, and robd from friend and foe,</l>
               <l>And fild vp holes, and dennes, and caues therewith:</l>
               <l>In truſt that men and meanes the way would worke,</l>
               <l>To make him king by others harme and hurt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And not content miſchiefe at home to warpe,</l>
               <l>In forraine parts like rancor he did plot,</l>
               <l>To ioyne with him he drew the Spaniards in,</l>
               <l>For men, for money, and what els he could:</l>
               <l>Suppoſing by that meanes about to bring,</l>
               <l>To diſpoſſeſſe the Queene and make him king.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>More firme to purchaſe his aſpiring thoughts,</l>
               <l>In priuate corners all about the land,</l>
               <l>In ſecret manner he had drawne to him,</l>
               <l>All hollow hearts and thoſe of Popiſh marke:</l>
               <l>This monſter thus his poiſon forth had blowne,</l>
               <l>And hop'd at laſt to reape what he had ſowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:12"/>
               <l>But the proud <hi>Hamon</hi> when he thought all ſure,</l>
               <l>Was fartheſt off his purpoſe and intent:</l>
               <l>God ſits on high, and ſees mens acts on earth,</l>
               <l>And topſie turuie throwes the wicked downe:</l>
               <l>All ages tels, experience proues it plaine,</l>
               <l>In moſt extreames God raiſeth helpe againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To buckle with this Archrebell <hi>Tyrone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God mou'd the Queene and Nobles of her land,</l>
               <l>To mount to ſtate <hi>Mountioy</hi> faithfull Peere,</l>
               <l>That by his hight might <hi>Tyrone</hi> trample downe:</l>
               <l>And by the Sun-beames ſpreading from his creſt,</l>
               <l>The Rebels heart teare from his traitors breaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And bleſſed beames, ſince firſt they gaue their light,</l>
               <l>How hath the ſtreames which faire <hi>Mountioy</hi> ſpreads,</l>
               <l>Dazled the eyes of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and his traine,</l>
               <l>And dimbd their ſight like men thats blindfold led?</l>
               <l>For oft we ſee darke clowdes and foggie miſt,</l>
               <l>When Sun once ſhines, it driues them where it liſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Witneſſe the Moyrie where <hi>Mountioy</hi> lay,</l>
               <l>In fogs, in winds, in ſtormes and powring raine:</l>
               <l>Not for a night, a day, a weeke, or month,</l>
               <l>But more then fiftie daies and winter nights:</l>
               <l>When tents, when cabbins, cels, and ſhelters all,</l>
               <l>By whirling winds and ſtormes were forſt to fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cloſe by his ſide this ſubtile Serpent lay,</l>
               <l>And all the rabble of his rebell ſlaues,</l>
               <l>Like leering foxes in their hatefull dennes,</l>
               <l>All furniſht well for to maintaine their broile:</l>
               <l>But when as once <hi>Mountioy</hi> came in ſight,</l>
               <l>The ſnailes drew in their heads and durſt not fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:12"/>
               <l>There did <hi>Mountioy</hi> tyre this <hi>Tyrone</hi> well;</l>
               <l>There did his beames his darkeſt trench make ſhine,</l>
               <l>There did <hi>Mountioy</hi> traine him to the field;</l>
               <l>There was <hi>Tyrone</hi> beat from his ſtrongeſt hold,</l>
               <l>And in the end a cowards part did play,</l>
               <l>For like falſe Rebels there they ſtole away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But like himſelfe <hi>Mountioy</hi> mounted yet,</l>
               <l>And with the brightnes of his flying beames,</l>
               <l>Found out the Rebell and his damned crue,</l>
               <l>Who in Armah were cloſe and ſlylie laid:</l>
               <l>For why the Moyrie had ſo curbd the cur,</l>
               <l>That he and whelps were glad to run ſo fur.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There did theſe ſnakes roule round their tailes a while,</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt were forſt to caſt their skinnes,</l>
               <l>Like coward cocks that thinkes their dunghils beſt,</l>
               <l>Durſt not abide Armah, where they were in:</l>
               <l>For why <hi>Mountioy</hi> hurld bullets in ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>As to Blackwater they were forſt at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There in their faſtnes cloſely they were laid,</l>
               <l>Like hogs in ſties, or dogs in kinnels vile,</l>
               <l>Like priuie theeues that beſt loues darkſome night,</l>
               <l>And hates the Sunne for feare of being ſeene:</l>
               <l>So they in bogs and buſhes ſecret lay,</l>
               <l>To kill and murther all that paſt that way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſtill <hi>Mountioy</hi> ſent forth his brightſome beames,</l>
               <l>To let theſe vipers know he was not farre,</l>
               <l>And ſpeedily Blackwater ouer went,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and his boggie crue:</l>
               <l>Moyrie, Mountnorris, and Blackwater fort,</l>
               <l>Shewes our <hi>Mountioy</hi> holds <hi>Tyrone</hi> but a ſport.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:13"/>
               <l>And well it ſeemes he found his combe neere cut,</l>
               <l>Which made him ſend poſt vpon poſt in ſpeed,</l>
               <l>His prieſts and Friers flocked faſt to Spaine,</l>
               <l>Well loden all with packs and ſacks of lyes:</l>
               <l>His bleſſed father now the Pope muſt helpe,</l>
               <l>Or els is like to loſe his chiefeſt whelpe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as in fine it proued to be true,</l>
               <l>His plots and letters tooke impreſſion there,</l>
               <l>His holy father thought it now high time,</l>
               <l>To helpe his grandchild to darke <hi>Mountioyes</hi> light:</l>
               <l>And for his aide the Pope did ſo preuaile,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Don Iohn</hi> landed ſhortly at Kinſale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There did he ſeate and trench himſelfe full faſt,</l>
               <l>And mand ſuch Caſtles as he found ſtood nigh,</l>
               <l>Foure thouſand ſtrong he found himſelfe to be,</l>
               <l>And made no doubt but to obtaine the game:</l>
               <l>For looke what art or policie could doe,</l>
               <l>To make all ſure <hi>Don Iohn</hi> did ſhifts purſue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nothing was wanting but the Rebels aide,</l>
               <l>Which when they heard that <hi>Don Iohn</hi> was ſo nigh,</l>
               <l>Their fainting heart began to come againe,</l>
               <l>And with ſtrong vowes proteſteth ſtraight to come:</l>
               <l>And with ſuch ſpeede as Rebels well could make,</l>
               <l>To aide the Spaniard they doe vndertake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Odonnell</hi> with three thouſand horſe and foote,</l>
               <l>Set forward firſt, like furies come from hell,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tyrone</hi> the traitor haſted with his ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Moſt vgly ſlaues like to the former ſort,</l>
               <l>Well furniſhed, as is their beaſtly guiſe,</l>
               <l>With armes and victuals to obtaine the prize.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:13"/>
               <l>But happie <hi>Mountioy</hi> hauing heard theſe newes,</l>
               <l>Drew downe his forces towards Kinſale ſtraight,</l>
               <l>And nigh <hi>Don Iohn</hi> began for to approch,</l>
               <l>To know the cauſe and buſines he had there:</l>
               <l>And as the beaſt that's pind vp in the ſtye,</l>
               <l>He keepes <hi>Don Iohn</hi> that out he could not flye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There did he campe ſtoutly with all his force,</l>
               <l>There made he trenches fit for ſouldiers vſe,</l>
               <l>There made he mounts to batter downe the walles,</l>
               <l>There made he forts for to offend the foe:</l>
               <l>There from ſuch Caſtles that the Spaniard held,</l>
               <l>By force of armes perforce he was expeld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here who had ſeene for more then fifteene weekes,</l>
               <l>The lying of our armie at Kinſale,</l>
               <l>In open aire, no ſhelter for reliefe,</l>
               <l>Beaten ſtill with winde, haile, ſnow, raine, and froſt,</l>
               <l>With thunderclaps and fearfull flames of fire,</l>
               <l>Their faireſt footing was but durt and mire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In all which time ranke Rebels held aloofe,</l>
               <l>Beating their braines and plotting all they could,</l>
               <l>Choaking the aire with their infectious breath,</l>
               <l>Fearing the beames would burne from <hi>Mountioy</hi> cames</l>
               <l>For oft before they triall good had made,</l>
               <l>To meete them boldly <hi>Mountioy</hi> was not fraid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt a remnant ſent from out of Spaine,</l>
               <l>Who winds and ſeas kept houering vp and downe,</l>
               <l>Arriued where <hi>Tyrone</hi> might aide them well,</l>
               <l>In number full a thouſand fighting men:</l>
               <l>Whereby the Rebels better courage tooke,</l>
               <l>Being then in ſtrength ſixe thouſand horſe and foote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:14"/>
               <l>Oh, who had ſeene theſe black bands come from Spaine.</l>
               <l>With Antichriſt their maſters banner ſpred,</l>
               <l>Stoutly aduanced, ſpreading in the aire,</l>
               <l>Richly ſet out with Chriſts fiue bleeding wounds:</l>
               <l>And quartred with ſuppoſed <hi>Peters</hi> keyes,</l>
               <l>With other tricks which might well babies pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What deadly curſes were there thundred out,</l>
               <l>Gainſt thoſe that to this ſtanderd beare diſdaine?</l>
               <l>How deepe to Limbo were all good men throwne?</l>
               <l>Booke, bell, and candle curſt them all to hell:</l>
               <l>Their Agnus deis, Crucifix, and Beades,</l>
               <l>Were roundly dealt by thoſe this black gard leades.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But who had ſeene how <hi>Tyrone</hi> and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Had ſhar'd the bootie fore the field was won,</l>
               <l>And with black pennes did dawbe their bloodie books,</l>
               <l>Of thoſe whoſe heads in triumph they would beare;</l>
               <l>Would muſe to heare, and wonder at the ſlaue,</l>
               <l>That ſhould to Prince and countrie ſuch ſpite haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now gan the diuell laugh and ſmile a pace,</l>
               <l>To ſee his imps bent to their curſed wils:</l>
               <l>For now it was concluded without let,</l>
               <l>The Spaniards ſhould relieued preſent be:</l>
               <l>And to that end a meſſenger was ſent,</l>
               <l>To tell <hi>Don Iohn</hi> their purpoſe and intent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On Chriſtmas eue hard at the breake of day,</l>
               <l>Appointed was that they would certaine come;</l>
               <l>And while on one ſide they would freſhly charge,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Don Iohn</hi> by force ſhould iſſue from the towne:</l>
               <l>By which attempt they thought by force and might,</l>
               <l>To win the field and darke <hi>Mountioyes</hi> light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:14"/>
               <l>But our great God whoſe ſeate is heauens throne,</l>
               <l>And for his footſtoole hath the maſsie earth,</l>
               <l>Who rules and guides the hearts of mortall men,</l>
               <l>Without whoſe will a ſillie bird fals not:</l>
               <l>Who lets men plot and hammer what they will,</l>
               <l>Yet as he pleaſe it is effected ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He held proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> from his curſed will;</l>
               <l>He curbed <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and the reſt;</l>
               <l>He hang'd fiue Kings that Iſraels peace diſturb'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeb</hi> he threw downe to the ground:</l>
               <l>He cauſed <hi>Hamon</hi> trie the gibbet furſt,</l>
               <l>And ſtout <hi>Goliahs</hi> forehead to be burſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He neuer leaues thoſe that put truſt in him;</l>
               <l>His workes are great, his mercie farre exceeds;</l>
               <l>He ſtill rewards all men as they deſerue;</l>
               <l>He puls downe proud men, and ſets vp the weake:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tyrons</hi> falſe heart the Lord full well hath ſeene,</l>
               <l>And will defend a true and lawfull Queene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For all the ſecret working of theſe imps,</l>
               <l>He ſoone can bring their counſels vnto naught;</l>
               <l>He findes the meanes <hi>Mountioy</hi> ſhall preuent,</l>
               <l>Their purpoſes and enterpriſes all:</l>
               <l>And in his hand holds faſt the turning wheele,</l>
               <l>That lifts ſome vp, ſome backward makes to reele.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As well appeares by this which doth inſue:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mountioy</hi> hauing knowledge of their plot,</l>
               <l>Drew forth not paſt one thouſand of his foote,</l>
               <l>Three hundred horſe was all he tooke along:</l>
               <l>And eaſily he led them on the way,</l>
               <l>With purpoſe full to keepe the Rebels play.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:15"/>
               <l>Quickly he might the enemies behold,</l>
               <l>All marſhalled with drums and colours ſpread,</l>
               <l>Guided by Leaders of their beſt commaund,</l>
               <l>In battailes plac'd, with wings laid for the time:</l>
               <l>With Lions lookes they made a ſtaring ſtand,</l>
               <l>With good aduice to take the fight in hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now doth <hi>Mountioyes</hi> beames begin to ſpread,</l>
               <l>His preſence dims theſe Rebels ſights forthwith,</l>
               <l>And gallantly his horſe doth giue the charge,</l>
               <l>And drawes his foote to offer them the like:</l>
               <l>They charge againe, <hi>Mountioyes</hi> horſe then flie out,</l>
               <l>And ruſhed in amidſt the ſtrongeſt rout.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iehoua</hi> now gaue courage to our men,</l>
               <l>And in the Rebels ſtrike a ſlauiſh feare:</l>
               <l>For in a minuit of a time, they gan</l>
               <l>To breake their rankes and throw their armes away:</l>
               <l>And well was he that beſt could run or ride,</l>
               <l>To trie their valour none durſt there abide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They being broke, God ſo did ſtrength <hi>Mountioy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And bleſt the labour of his worthie men,</l>
               <l>That they with ſpeed purſu'd the Rebell ſlaues,</l>
               <l>And in a moment had twelue hundred kild:</l>
               <l>Nine Colours won, and many captiues tane,</l>
               <l>Two thouſand armes they loſt vnto their ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In their purſute the riuers plaid their part,</l>
               <l>And riſing vp againſt ſuch wicked imps,</l>
               <l>Their mounting waues did ſinke them to the deepe,</l>
               <l>As moſt vnworthie to enioy the land:</l>
               <l>Happie was he could ſhun that bloodie day,</l>
               <l>And ſtouteſt man that made moſt haſte away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:15"/>
               <l>There might you ſee a iuſt reuenge for blood,</l>
               <l>Blood cries for blood, for in each dike and gap,</l>
               <l>They groueling lay beſprinkled all with blood:</l>
               <l>One legleſſe lay, another wants his arme:</l>
               <l>Some all to cut and mangled back and face,</l>
               <l>That ſtreames of blood were ſhed in euery place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There might you ſee from Eaſt, Weſt, North and South,</l>
               <l>The Rauens, Crowes, and foules in flocks to come:</l>
               <l>There might you ſee from euery den and buſh,</l>
               <l>The greedie wolues and rauening beaſts make haſte:</l>
               <l>As welcome gueſts vnto ſo fat a feaſt,</l>
               <l>They cheer'd themſelues as well the moſt as leaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beſides all this, aboue ſeauen hundred men,</l>
               <l>Were wounded ſore and hurt in grieuous wiſe;</l>
               <l>There might you heare them howling with loude cries;</l>
               <l>There might you ſee them ſtampe and ſtare apace;</l>
               <l>There might you ſee them languiſh and make mone,</l>
               <l>Yet little helpe or ſuccour to them ſhowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus by Gods helpe <hi>Mountioy</hi> was the meane,</l>
               <l>To daunt the pride of thoſe Arch-rebels all;</l>
               <l>And that ſame pit which they for others made,</l>
               <l>Their curſed feete lay caught in the ſame gin.</l>
               <l>And as this fell, ſo Lord let be thy will,</l>
               <l>When next they meete like hap ſend Rebels ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus are theſe men who vnderhand before,</l>
               <l>Had caſt their cards with truſt to get the game,</l>
               <l>All male content raging in great extreames,</l>
               <l>Curſing their chance, returne with all the loſſe;</l>
               <l>Railing the Spaniſh, ſaying this and that,</l>
               <l>To be the cauſe of this their hard miſhap.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:16"/>
               <l>But had you ſeene theſe Rebels in their flight,</l>
               <l>When as our forces neuer made purſute,</l>
               <l>Tweene Cork and Mallo as they paſt along,</l>
               <l>What fearfull fits amazed all their thoughts?</l>
               <l>Each buſh and blaſt, each ſhadow made them ſay,</l>
               <l>Here comes <hi>Mountioy,</hi> therefore make haſte away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ſome of his that were falne in the reare,</l>
               <l>Strooke ſuch a terror in his formoſt men,</l>
               <l>That downe goes armes and weapons in great haſte,</l>
               <l>Doubting our forces had been at their heeles:</l>
               <l>But loe Gods hand the wicked to confound,</l>
               <l>In Mallow foord two hundred there lay drown'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There who had ſeene the Iriſh loue to Spaine,</l>
               <l>For whoſe defence the Spaniard thither came,</l>
               <l>And for their ſakes left children, wife and friends,</l>
               <l>What crueltie to them theſe Rebels ſhew'd:</l>
               <l>They murthred ſome, ſome ſtrip'd vnto their skin,</l>
               <l>And let them lie to ſinke or elſe to ſwim.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus were theſe traitors all diſperſt abroad,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tyrone</hi> himſelfe came home not with eight men:</l>
               <l>His heart was faint, for Aquavite cals,</l>
               <l>His welcome home was ſad and heauie lookes:</l>
               <l>Wiſhing they had the Spaniſh left alone,</l>
               <l>And like falſe Rebels ſtill haue ſtaid at home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Odonnell</hi> hatefull traitor to the world,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Mustion</hi> too, ſail'd are into Spaine;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tyrrill</hi> the Rebell tarries ſtill behinde,</l>
               <l>VVith new ſtart Rebels ſprung vp very late:</l>
               <l>VVhoſe curſed ends no doubt will ſhortly ſhow,</l>
               <l>God hates the works which from ſuch wretches flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:16"/>
               <l>Now Rebels all and Papiſts of this land,</l>
               <l>You head-ſhorne Friers, and you lying Prieſts,</l>
               <l>See what vaine hope is in your popiſh traſh,</l>
               <l>Your popiſh ſtanderd was not worth a ſtraw:</l>
               <l>Runne therefore headlong, howle, crie and mone,</l>
               <l>Throughout the world your ſhame &amp; loſſe is blowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mountioy</hi> he returnes back to Kinſale,</l>
               <l>VVith praiſe to God for ſuch a bleſſed day,</l>
               <l>Attributing the glorie to the Lord,</l>
               <l>In all which fight he loſt not full three men:</l>
               <l>And ſouldiers loden were with booties good,</l>
               <l>As iuſt rewards for ventring of their blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here muſt I marſhall in their iuſt deſert,</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>George Carew</hi> of Munſter Preſident,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe coſt, whoſe care, and trauell in theſe broiles,</l>
               <l>Liuely laies downe his loue to Prince and ſtate:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thomond, Clenrickerd,</hi> and Lord <hi>Awdley</hi> eke,</l>
               <l>Like to themſelues true honour there did ſeeke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir <hi>Richard Wingfield,</hi> Marſhall of the field,</l>
               <l>VVith Sir <hi>George Bourchier</hi> well deſerueth praiſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dauers,</hi> and <hi>Lambert, Power, Barley</hi> too,</l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Laurence, Bagnall, Folliot,</hi> and <hi>Ruſh:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Godolphin, Greame,</hi> with <hi>Taaffe,</hi> and Captaines all,</l>
               <l>Honour haue got by Rebels loſſe and fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All this ſame while <hi>Don Iohn</hi> lay very cloſe,</l>
               <l>Expecting ſtill when Rebels promiſe held:</l>
               <l>At laſt got knowledge of the traitors chance,</l>
               <l>VVhich made him hang his head like Spaniſh vſe:</l>
               <l>He bit his nailes, he leerd vp to the skie,</l>
               <l>He ſtampt the ground, and muſing long did lie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:17"/>
               <l>Hope in <hi>Tyrone,</hi> that courſe he thought was vaine;</l>
               <l>Hope in himſelfe, he ſaw ſmall comfort there;</l>
               <l>Hope out of Spaine, he knew that would be long;</l>
               <l>Hope for to fight, he found leſſe ioy in that.</l>
               <l>At laſt he ſtarted from his doubtfull muſe,</l>
               <l>To call a parley he thought beſt to chuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Forthwith his Drum was ſent to ſhew his minde:</l>
               <l>But happie <hi>Mountioy</hi> had no like thereof,</l>
               <l>Whoſe purpoſe was to ſtarue and beate him out,</l>
               <l>As fitteſt guerdon for his bold attempt:</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill to call for parley he was bold,</l>
               <l>And marſhall men muſt marſhall orders hold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Parley obtaind, conditions were agreed,</l>
               <l>Good quarter held according to contract,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mountioy</hi> pleaſde, <hi>Don Iohn</hi> was well content,</l>
               <l>Of deadly hate more quiet did inſue:</l>
               <l>Where otherwiſe, if both had ſtill held out,</l>
               <l>Much loſſe of blood had brought Kinſale about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By which contract and compoſition made,</l>
               <l>Perforce muſt make all Spaniards Engliſh loue:</l>
               <l>And graunt that Engliſh thirſt not after blood,</l>
               <l>But mercie, loue, peace, and all charitie:</l>
               <l>Which ornaments both God and man doth like,</l>
               <l>And oft preuailes more then doth bloodie fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beſides, this courſe in reaſon needs muſt moue,</l>
               <l>The Spaniſh nation Iriſh Rebels hate,</l>
               <l>By whoſe preſumes and vile inticing traines,</l>
               <l>Were hither drawne into ſo hard extreames:</l>
               <l>And make them graunt while life they doe endure,</l>
               <l>A Rebels word and ſtrength is moſt vnſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:17"/>
               <l>And eke the courſe <hi>Mountioy</hi> tooke therein,</l>
               <l>May draw the Spaniſh hate to Engliſh loue,</l>
               <l>Their Iriſh loue vnto a mortall iarre,</l>
               <l>And Iriſh truſt no more to Spaniſh arme:</l>
               <l>England and Spaine by this may quiet bee,</l>
               <l>And Spaine no more the Iriſh loue to ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this the world, the Pope, and King of Spaine,</l>
               <l>May iudge the conqueſt that <hi>Don Iohn</hi> hath got,</l>
               <l>Who bluſtred out halfe Ireland he had won,</l>
               <l>And at whoſe fortune they did ſo admire,</l>
               <l>May now perceiue that Rebels, Prieſts, and Friers,</l>
               <l>Coine naught but lies to fit their owne deſires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And hereby may the King of Spaine obſerue,</l>
               <l>How God abhors and hates vniuſt attempts,</l>
               <l>And leaue his hate gainſt faire ELIZABETH,</l>
               <l>Virgin Queene, famous for vertuous life:</l>
               <l>And blot no more his honour with diſgrace,</l>
               <l>To backe baſe Rebels in ſo bad a caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto which end, marke but Gods hand herein,</l>
               <l>The Spaniſh preſent gins to ſhew their loue,</l>
               <l>Hard by Kinſale ſome bands of Engliſh lay,</l>
               <l>After the armie was diſſolu'd and gon:</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Tyrril</hi> and new Rebels did deuiſe,</l>
               <l>By ſtrength and force theſe bands for to ſurpriſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereof the Spaniſh hauing notice got,</l>
               <l>Drew forth their men to ioyne with ours ſtraight,</l>
               <l>With ſolemne vowes, there for to liue and die</l>
               <l>In Engliſh right, and Rebels for to foile:</l>
               <l>Thus thoſe which lately ſought for Engliſh blood,</l>
               <l>Will ſhed their owne to doe our countrie good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4833:18"/>
               <l>Now ſith <hi>Iehoua</hi> of his mercie great,</l>
               <l>Wonderouſly hath fought in his owne cauſe,</l>
               <l>And giuen now <hi>Mountioy</hi> for to ſee,</l>
               <l>That counſell, horſe, and men get not the field:</l>
               <l>But whom God loues, and thoſe who ſerue him ſtill,</l>
               <l>Are ſure to conquer as their owne ſelues will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then let ELIZA reſt ſtill on Gods ſtrong hand,</l>
               <l>Obey his lawes, aduance his Goſpell pure,</l>
               <l>Roote out blind Papiſts, Prieſts, and filthie Friers,</l>
               <l>Bring all degrees to heare Gods holy word:</l>
               <l>Cheriſh the good, ſnub ſuch as wicked are,</l>
               <l>And then ELIZA ſhall proſper in the war.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4833:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
